Ivoryton Congregational Church Collection
Ivoryton Library Association
Ivoryton Congregational Church Collection
1844-2017
1898-2015
Ivoryton Congregational Church (Ivoryton, Conn.)
2017.001
12 lf. 22 Boxes, wooden pulpit and framed attendance chart
Ivoryton Library Association
The collection primarily consists of records and photographs of the Ivoryton Congregational Church, 1844-2017.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the board of trustees of the Ivoryton Congregational Church to the Ivoryton Library Association in 2017.
Biography
Prior to 1877, Ivoryton residents who wished to attend Congregational services travelled to the church in Centerbrook, CT. In 1877, the Ivoryton segment of the congregation began to meet at Comstock Hall (104 Main St in Ivoryton, second floor). Memorial Chapel was built in Ivoryton in 1888 by the Comstock family of Comstock, Cheney & Co., the ivory processing factory and main employer of the village. The congregation remained a part of the Centerbrook church until 1898 when members voted to form a separate church and became the Ivoryton Congregational Church. The building was put up for sale in March, 2017. As of 2018, the congregation worships in space provided by the Essex Congregational Church.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ivoryton Congregational Church Collection consists primarily of written records including minutes of the church board and the Society of Church Workers (1897-1966), annual reports (1960-2018), Sunday School records (1888-1915) and church treasurer's records (1898-1944.) There are 8 boxes of photographs (1892-2016), including photographs of the original congregation members, the earliest pastors and deacons as well as many church events. Also included are documents, history and anniversary pamphlets, books, bibles, scrapbooks of church members, sheet music and hymnals, newspaper clippings. The names of Bessie Comstock, Sunday School teacher, and her sister Laura Comstock, organist, are frequently found throughout, as are names of other well-known families in Ivoryton history. The collection does not include current financial records.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: I: Photographs, arranged in chronological order and II: Documents, records, books and all other items.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Congregational Church (Ivoryton, Conn.)--History; Bibles--1850-1860.; Bibles--1860-1870.; Annual reports.; Minutes (records); Sheet music
Separated Material
The church pulpit is located in the main circulation room in the Ivoryton Library. The framed Sunday School attendance chart is located in the Oversize Local History area in the main circulation room of the Ivoryton Library.
Location Note
Ivoryton Library Local History Room
- Inventory
  - Documents and pamphlets, undated (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1960-1989 (Box 2)
  - Annual reports, 1890-2017 (Box 3)
  - Records-Society of Church workers, 1897-1966 (Box 4)
  - Handmade banner, hung in parish hall, circa 1970 (Box 5)
  - 5 History pamphlets, 1924 (Box 6)
  - framed photograph, 1947 (Box 6)
  - 5 copper plate photographic negative printing blocks, undated (Box 6)
  - In Remembrance' binder, undated (Box 6)
  - quotation calendar, 1907 (Box 6)
  - Sunday School record books, 1888-1915 (Box 7)
  - Pulpit Bible, 1859 (Box 8)
  - Memorial Chapel Bible, 1876 (Box 9)
  - Bible, undated (Box 10)
  - record books - Church treasurer, 1898-1994 (Box 11)
  - Centerbrook Congregational Church record book, contains by-laws, minutes, lists of members, marriages, baptisms and deaths, 1844-1914 (Box 12)
  - 3 record books - Society of Church Workers, 1922-1945 (Box 12)
  - Record book - Ivoryton Auxiliary of the New Haven branch of the Women’s Board of Foreign Missions, 1897-1924 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks by church members, 1888-1930 (Box 12)
  - 4 hymnals, 1875-1947 (Box 12)
  - Sheet music folio, 1893 (Box 12)
  - Bibles, 1871-1902 (Box 12)
  - Fundraiser cookbooks, 1980-2015 (Box 12)
  - Personalized Plate w/ church image, 1963 (Box 13)
  - Sunday School attendance chart, circa 1950 (Box *)
  - Wooden Pulpit, pre 1888 (Box *)
  - Early photographs mounted on board, undated (Box Photo 1)
  - Early photographs mounted on board, undated (Box Photo 2)
  - Events, 1959-1986 (Box Photo 3)
  - Falls River Flood, 1982 (Box Photo 4)
  - Events, 1987-1988 (Box Photo 5)
  - Events, 1989-1992 (Box Photo 6)
  - Quilt shows, 1985-1895 (Box Photo 7)
  - Events, 2000-2016 (Box Photo 8)